right now sweet
yeah so i i was just saying you guys did
a wonderful
uh narration about this issue of
rationality how
uh you know sort of the foundationalists
the rationalists are thinking about it
and how we need to break out of that
and then how as you lean into that you
start to intersect with faith
i thought that rocked yeah and you
wanted to give a summary of your
conversation about consciousness
yeah well i can certainly give you a
snippet of where i'm coming from and
then you know john and i actually i
think are
complementing each other here so you
know my life's work one way to frame my
life's works is on the problem of
psychology
okay so the problem of psychology i
actually did a blog went a little viral
on it just recently was
we should know about the problem of
psychology and the way we know about the
problem of quantum gravity
okay and what i mean by that is everyone
should be aware
that the field of psychology has
struggled forever is try to define
what the hell it is as a science of okay
and to this day it remains is it a
science of mind
is it science of behavior or is the
science of some combination in therein
and there is no language system that
allows you
to clarify what is meant by a science of
say mind and behavior that's the normal
blending all right and we should be
really conscious of that
um you know not to make a pun on words
here okay
uh and it's right quite remarkable i
mean we've known this since 1927
led vygotsky really nails it and uh it
calls it the crisis of psychology
um never been resolved and it's at the
to me it's at the foundation of what i
call the enlightenment gap
the enlightenment gaps the modernist
inability to develop
a language system that's coherent enough
uh to define
the necessary terms in the field of
relation
so that we get coherence and that's what
my
system is about i'm you know what i'm
working on is the behavior
and mind mind mind problem okay and what
i mean by that is
you have to sort out what is behavior
what do you mean by that
and then there's actually three
different definitions of mind that have
to be
disentangled uh for you to actually have
a language system that then
has the appropriate references and when
you do that then all of a sudden
the field uh becomes much less tangled
and you start to be able to talk with
coherence
so the uh how this
and how this dialogues and that's what
greg and i are doing in each episode
dialogues with the uh what's called the
hard problem of consciousness
is we uh there's a long argument there
it's very similar
in sort of uh structure to what went on
an awakening from the meeting crisis
there's first of all historical analysis
of how did we get to the culture of
cognitive grammar that has made
this aspect of ourselves that is so
familiar and personal
so deeply deeply problematic and we
first of all take a look at sort of the
cartesian arguments
and the main point there is um
the the what's called the mind body
problem the problem of the relationship
between
consciousness and our material existence
our physical existence is better said by
the way
than material um is enmeshed it is woven
together with
and is inseparable from the cultural
cognitive grammar of the scientific
revolution i made similar arguments and
awakening for the meaning crisis
and then expanding that out um and
and then so how that problem which is
right what greg referred to the
generation of uh
of of the world view of modernity uh
became then a mesh into what greg calls
the problem of psychology
is our endeavor to do a lot more work at
setting up
the problem formulating the problem of
consciousness really clearly
and what comes out of that is there are
there are two issues
that tend to be separated in
professional academic discourse about
consciousness there's
the generation or nature question
which is how does something like
consciousness be how does it have a
place within
the physical world as described by
science like how does
one way of putting that although it's
always it's also everything you say
about consciousness is contentious
is how does consciousness emerge from
the physical world
um and greg and i are and this is how it
also meshes with craig's work
uh part of the argument there is you
know that
that's that question is ill-posed we
should be asking a deeper question
of you know how does life emerge out of
non-life
um how does sentience emerge out of
animate life and then how does
consciousness relate
so it's much more of a continuum
question than the stark contrast
and then that is put into dialogue with
the other question which is well what
does consciousness do
i mean for descartes there was no
question but because because he's
pre-freud
and pre-chomsky but given that most of
our intelligent behavior doesn't seem to
require consciousness what is it that
consciousness
does for us that's the function question
the point is we have theories
cognitive scientific neuroscientific
theories that tend to address one
one of these questions the nature
question the generation question
or the function question but not the two
together part part of the argument that
i'm presenting and greg is
uh helping me with is that that's that's
also a fundamental mistake of analysis
the two questions are deeply integrated
and although it's harder
we have to try and frame them and answer
them in an integrated fashion and then
there's a long argument about that but
the main idea is
that the function of consciousness
is to do uh to to do what i call
aspectualization
um aspectualization is out of all the
properties
i zero in on the relevant subset of this
thing
how they're relevant to each other and
how they're relevant to me
and although i have to say that in three
ways those are all just one relevance
realization package
so right now this is a phone but it
could be a weapon
it could be a platform right and the
point is
i'm always aspectualizing and then the
idea is that
aspectualization which um is
basically a process in which relevance
is becoming
salient in the sense that it's arousing
your
investment of your time and your energy
as specialization
is what makes so your brain
as a your body brain
as a physical thing has co-variations
with the
world right it has mental states that
reliably co-vary
and that can actually explain a lot of
your even unconscious behavior
reliable covariation the problem with
covariation and this is a standard issue
is that covariation isn't doesn't have
the precision of representation right so
the thing in the world that's co-varying
with this is it covering with it as a
phone
as a tool as an object as a platform as
a potential weapon
as a thing given to me on my birthday
etc right and so and this act this idea
actually comes from descartes many
people don't know that
know this what consciousness does is it
takes the reliable co-variations that
give us our root america rudimentary
intelligence our ability to respond
in a reliable reliably discriminatory
variable fashion with the variations of
the world and what it does is it
aspectualizes them for us
and when they're asked spectralized
they're now ready for reason
they're ready for and i'm meaning that
very broadly and greg is being
charitable with me on that so
right uh i i love the frame i can frank
you know what
i love it yeah no right and so um
the idea is that that's one of the main
functions of
uh consciousness that's why
consciousness is so needed
in situations where we're facing novelty
complexity
or ambiguity because aspect realization
is needed
and what i can show and i'm not going to
do it here because there's too much not
enough time
is most of the functional accounts that
i made this argument elsewhere
most of the current functional accounts
of consciousness actually converge on
this idea
of consciousness is this kind of higher
order relevance realization
aspectualization that readies us for
reason
in a powerful way now what that also
gives i would argue is it also starts to
explain the phenomenology
why well what does a spectralization
give
give you well it gives you what i call
the adverbial qualia
it gives you the hereness and the
nowness
and the togetherness the adverbial
quality
and the problem that has sort of
hamstrung
a lot of discourse about consciousness
is that we over focus on the adjectival
quality
the greenness the blueness and what's
coming
what it and what and i'm not going to
say that those aren't part of
consciousness of course they are
but the adverbial qualia are actually
qualia
and they can actually be so they're part
of the nature
of consciousness it's what it's like to
be conscious
but they are directly explicable in
terms of the functionality
now what might that do for you well it
might help to account for the fact
that you can actually have states of
consciousness in which there are no
adjectival qualia
you can be in the pure conscious event
that's achieved indeed
but what doesn't go away are the
adverbial qualia
the hereness and the noun that's why
like the these
these states are described with
superlatives of hereness and nowness
eternity and unity ultimate togetherness
so the adverbial qualia
are seem to be both necessary and
sufficient
for consciousness and that that seems to
be
um there's more to this i'm just giving
you a gist
now what this ultimately leads to is
this idea
you have participatory knowing that set
up the reliable covariation
and generate affordances and then you
have
right this higher order relevance
realization
that is right that is doing the aspect
realization and that gives me my
perspective knowing
and consciousness is my participatory
knowing
of and through my perspectival knowing
that's why
when i'm conscious i'm not only what's
it like it's also who i am
i know i'm conscious by being conscious
and so i'm trying to give an account
that in an integrated fashion explains
the functionality
and the phenomenality of consciousness
and it also helps to explain a deep
intuition
that is presupposed but never addressed
through all of this literature
that we attribute consciousness where we
where we have evidence for intelligence
people reliably do that well here's a
reason why because there's a deep
continuity and functional relationship
between the relevance realization that
gets the covariation going
and the higher order relevance
realization that aspectualizes that
and readies it for reason
boom that's it and that of course
everything i said
pretty much every single sentence needs
argument and evidence
and what greg and i are doing is
unpacking the argument and the evidence
right nice so yeah for me that
all of that fits uh it all fits in my
unified theory frame
uh it and so what john is doing so so
very quickly
i said there are three different really
meanings of the word mind
mental process okay so one meeting what
i call mind one
uh that's a neurocognitive functional
account
of mental behavior i'll say that again
it's a neurocognitive functional account
of mental behavior so what you do there
is you see an animal behaving
i got fish over there i go up i feed
them every time i feed them they get all
excited
okay why well there's a classical and
opera and associative relationship
and i can analyze the hierarchical
structure of their nervous system
relate it to the contingencies of the
environment and analyze the animal
behavioral patterns in relationship to
that
where the cognitive refers to the
information instantiated within the
nervous system
and the mental over mental behavior
refers to what i see so that's a pure
science externalized view okay
and that's what some people mean when
they talk about mind it's like oh that's
the
that's the neurocognitive structure that
are regulating controlling behavior
that's one definition and you then
divide it up into all the stuff inside
the brain
the informational architecture and then
how it's regulating the stuff outside
that's between the animal and the
environment that's
what i call mental behavior because you
have to have that actual specifier
because atoms behave cells behave but
they don't behave as mental entities
okay then what you get is mind two of an
emergent function
which is essentially conscious
phenomenology what john's
theory is of is of the processes by
which
uh that neurocognitive architecture
comes together engages in perspectival
and participatory knowing
that's mind two now mind two is funky
okay and really challenging especially
in the language of science
because it's you can't see it right it's
epistemologically contained
unlike mind one which is
epistemologically available from a
science perspective
mind two is epistemologically across uh
the gap of first and second person
okay and that's a nightmare and that's
that's why science is fucking
tumbled over but then you get mine three
okay mind three is human justification
we just listened to john's mind three
give us a narrative about his theory of
consciousness
right now the cool thing about mind
three is that goes between across the
skin without a boundary
all right so the information contained
in my head as i talk
and through my skin so it's actually
intersubjectively available
from interior exterior positions so mind
one
is available through the exterior and
its classic neurocognitive behavioral
position
mind two is phenomenology consciousness
and then how does that work which is
john's fundamental theory and actually
lines right up with the
unified theory with enormous specificity
and precision and john's got some
brilliant insight that
adjectival versus adverbial shift my
mind went boom when i saw it
mine just did i mean when you just
brought it up first time i heard that
what the
i was like oh my god it's the witnessing
function and what you're witnessing
together and you split those things and
then you can have a pure consciousness
event as you find in meditation which
means then the qualia go away but you're
still present with the hereness now and
this
um uh it's it's boom you know so now you
actually then hone in you split that
thing off and my whole
the first thing i stumbled on in 1996
was the justification
hypothesis and theory which is what is
the mind three
what is the fundamental organization of
human mind three you guys were talking
about rationality last time and i wanted
to jump in there and say
hey actually guys use justification and
then split it across personal and social
and analytic
and you will be able to manage your
rationality narrative there
um that's another conversation but
anyway mind three is a totally different
ball game
because it cuts right through the skin
so we got to divide up
mind three mind two mind one and then
there's another argument for what
behavior is but
you do that we start talking with a
level of specificity and clarity
uh that's never been achieved and then
and the implications of that are hard to
overstate
so we probably i hope jordan we haven't
i mean you
you have an amazing capacity to take a
lot of complex information
um but i hope that wasn't like right but
we're geeking out here so we'll shut up
no that was great yeah it was fantastic
i liked all of it um
um no yeah so so thank you
and it'll take me a little while i think
to there's some eddies
like the the adjective adverb um
that i can feel them already doing stuff
i am changing as a consequence of that
that was a new thing
and it's real like it's a good thing um
and just for i just like to flag uh the
the the debatable
move that i think is consistently
showing up here that is so powerful you
need specificity and clarity like the
disambiguation it's like hey guys
a lot of the problem here is actually
just the grammar a lot of the problem is
that is the
is the things we're using to try to do
to figure stuff out
let's slow down let's get the tools in
order let's get things clear
once we get to clarity a lot of the
problems go away and those that don't go
away we can actually
now begin to dress um
yeah so it's really interesting and i
was noticing greg i just had in my mind
it popped into my mind
as you're talking at that last step um
systems of justification the the visual
image of the tree
because it's of course three you have
the trunk
it's all it's all this is happening in
the context of still the deep
fundamental connectedness to the whole
of real
and the way the whole of real is kind of
coming up in these stacks right so i've
got this
mind three which is sitting in mesh in
mind too which is sitting in machine
line one which is sitting and meshed in
you know all the way down to then you
know
reality and fully constrained by the
constraints that give rise to that
being a coherent structure all the way
up and then it has its own novel
or specifics of what it's doing in
that environment it opens up a lot of
adjacent possibles
when you shift into that language or
different information processing
right with that yeah so one one
argument in fact about the uh
one of the new theories and again i
won't go i'm not going to try and burden
people because
greg and i are going to unpack this in
detail but one of the more
most recent um and promising theories of
the function of consciousness um doesn't
agrees with that the idea of
consciousness is this aspect realization
um and but they also bring out
an important uh well i'm sorry i was
gonna i realized it was funny they're
gonna bring out an important aspect of
the aspect realization
uh but what's that aspect um and here
this is even tightening this idea about
reading it for reason i mean
aspectualization is what turns
co-variations into representations
and representations through their
specificity can become truth bearers
and that's needed for reason but what
aspect realization also does
and what consciousness seems to be
specifically needed for
is dealing with counter factuals
unconscious cognition doesn't seem to be
able to deal with
counter factuals right and so
what you're getting in the readiness or
reason is of course you're getting
representations which are truth bearers
right but there are unconscious
representations
but when they are aspectualized such
that they can enter into counter factual
consideration
then you have genuine readiness for
reason now of course that's going to
just be adaptively important
and of course when you recurse that on
yourself you get
a needed capacity for self-correction
because self-correction presupposes
i should have done x which is a counter
factual
right so i'll just add a quick comment
to that so
just so you were tracking here so when
he says ready for reason uh we're
talking still at an animal level
and for me then we're actually talking
then about okay ready for simulation
across possible paths of investment and
that's where the counterfactual will
come up so you're sort of like okay
i can now hold and by the way this then
connects into what's called working
memory
uh perspectival working memory so how
does the thing hold
and then run through various simulations
of possibility and then make comparison
relationship to possible passive
investment and create a cost-benefit
analysis of the affordances that you
want to then track
okay so then what happens is that's
happening at the mammal level
okay or birds a lot you know where
exactly is and all that's super crazy in
the animal world but essentially that's
what's going on
right and then actually i want to then
say yeah and then there's an extra ready
for reason that we do when we actually
start talking to each other
right which then said well how the hell
do you know you're not bullshitting me
you know it's right
yes there we are right and then you're
sort of like now i'm going to justify
now it's like why do you you know now
you have propositional language
actually tracking the simulation right
and then you have the question of the
proposition
now you have propositional knowledge on
top of perspectival participatory
knowledge
and then exactly right so so you're
talking about as i understand it is
something along the lines
of the the location in justification
justification space of what we might
call reason two
yeah yeah yep exactly yeah so which
within the mind three kind of reasoning
versus mind two kind of reasoning right
which is simulation
we do that all the time you imagine you
simulate various outcomes right
but it's not necessarily propositional
then you get into propositional knowing
okay and then what you what we got was
initially personal
and social indigenous justification and
then when we get in the pre-modern
formal and most notably socrates you
actually get formal analytic
epistemological justification which
well how do you know you're not just
fucking bullshitting it's like is it
here's math mathematical truths are like
this that's that's
that's deductive truths do we have
deductive truth systems that we're
actually moving or we're all just making
this up a bunch of
uh for our social needs and then now all
saying get philosophy and
boom real uh ah
so this implies by the way how neat i
believe that we just hit uh we
did this implies that when you've
achieved a particular level of
distributed
cognition that you've achieved the
capacity to actually have distributed
relevance realization
yes you will also have witnessed the
emergence of shared consciousness
yeah you have to be that i think that's
right
a whole bunch of new age people just had
a very weird feeling but yeah yeah yeah
not that one dude not not that one
no no no we're we're we're talking right
we're playing jazz here folks you know
okay
that kind of that's like that's you can
disambigue you can debibilize that what
i just said is exactly what is implied
just now you have to grasp it with the
right i think your point about so this
is actually you
your debibilization thing resonates
enormously to me that's what i've been
fucking obsessed with
because in 1990s i realized i was i was
equivocating i love john's word about
quibbling
equivocation yeah i was really i
realized that i was like i was getting
driven by something crazy and i didn't
have the word equivocate but that was
the issue
i didn't know what i was talking about
i'd listen to other people and they
didn't know what the hell they were
talking about i mean they knew within
their little frames but the frames
didn't line up so they're arguing about
stuff
that couldn't be corresponded to each
other so it's like what's the point
you know so anyway that's that's been my
obsession for a long damn time
let's let's sorry i want to make sure
you're done great because i know that's
something
i'm done
sorry you're also my friend and i want
to make sure that i i i
know yeah you don't have to worry about
your friend me brother
so about that about shared consciousness
i mean
dan chappie and i are doing a lot of
work on this because
about the rovers on mars and the
scientists working together to move the
rovers around
and that's where a lot of this stuff
about uh participatory perspective
knowing
really comes to the fore but let's try
something
let's let's move into that carefully
because i don't want to make the new
agers happy
uh but i do want to perhaps make us
ready for the next
uh paradigmatic place uh so uh
so let's take take a look at what we
were saying about notice
you know how we use these two terms
we sort of had awareness of the world
perception and then we had imagination
and we talked about working memory here
but the thing that we're now realizing
in cognitive sciences
those are not we sort of think of them
as different
but they're actually interwoven like
this right
then this is all what's going on what's
called predictive process
imagination is just the it's just the
top down
aspect of realization and perception is
just the bottom-up
aspect of it and you can pull them apart
uh in certain ways
but notice how consciousness is bridging
between them
because when i'm doing this on the world
i'm conscious
but when i'm doing this in my head you
know what i still am conscious
and consciousness is exactly that
bridging right that allow
that we're right we're bringing into
sort of a meta
cognitive awareness the the way we can
play with the relationship between the
top down and the bottom up
of aspectualization now something
analogous to that i think can go on
and i i i i want to be really
clear that i'm making an analogy here
something can go on in what is called
you know the social imaginary
the the kind of shared um
we've talked about this the paradigmatic
images and exemplars
that constitute a paradigm and then from
that
you know the groups of people have
shared awareness
of objects and relations in the world
and there's something analogous
it's not a consciousness but there's
something analogous to consciousness
moving between the social imaginary
and the socially shared awareness and
that is doing something very much like
you said
jordan it's doing relevance realization
it's managing relevance realization at
this
at the level of distributed cognition so
while i don't think that's a
consciousness
i think there is something analogous to
that
going on at the distributed cognitive
level
and that part of what we could be seeing
the potential of is a simultaneous
restructuring
of what that whatever we want to call
that is
and what's going on in here because
because we
we always think that this is the way
it's always been for us
our experience of consciousness the
greeks don't have a word for
consciousness
it doesn't exist for them the way it
exists for us as a phenomenon
right and so that we can we
it's quite likely we are have the
potential
to radically transform that outer i
don't know what to call it i don't want
to call it consciousness
but that outer analog of consciousness
and the inner experience of
consciousness in a very profound way
and i sometimes think jordan and i hope
you you find this complimentary
and not insulting i sometimes think
that i sometimes use that a way of
trying to understand what you're talking
about when you're talking about
coherence
yeah that feels right the word that word
just kept coming up for me and you know
greg's used
the that particular word a few times the
in the past a little in the past few
moments and
there's a a strong coordination there
so it's almost like you know i'm using
the word coherence
at the level of distributed cognition
yeah and then with a he's using the
level the word coherence in the at the
level of
mind uh i believe mine too
right and so the challenge is to say
okay how do you actually enable
coherence at the level of i think mine
three i may not be using that term just
right
no that's right yeah right yeah so so
here's so mind three then
is what it is that starts to connect us
on a highway of information
okay and then that's all that then rises
us from primates into people
okay that highway of information that
capacity to justify
that creates indigenous knowledge okay
and then ultimately we start building
civilizations then we get much more
material control and voila
but we get then the evolution of
cultural knowledge which are these
systems of justification that build upon
each other
all right and so when we do we get
plugged into cartesian dualism in a
particular kind of way
right that the greeks didn't so our
relationship to ourselves our relation
i think that shakespeare opened up a
soliloquy to ourself
right right in a totally different way
so we're getting this all this mind
mind three is kind of a blank slate it's
waiting to absorb
it's an organ of culture it's waiting to
absorb the narrative
and then bring you online and then we
feed those you feedback on it
okay yeah you know and so and what you
were talking when you guys
were talking remember the singularity
conversation you you riffed off the
singularity paper i gave right
and you instantaneously recognize that
we were changing paradigms
right accelerating paradigms in space
change
systems so what we're actually seeing is
this paradigmatic
you know flux crazy flux
all right those paradigms are these the
the center of these paradigms are
systems of justification
okay look at what peter lindberg did
with culture 2.0 he gets that table
he gets the archetypal justification the
anti-justification the leaders that
create the paradigm
this is what i stand for this is my
investment pattern these are my people
this is what i'm against
and what's happened is is that
technology intersection and
information is completely outstripping
any paradigm
that has for sense making capacity which
is driving the system insane
and what we're actually trying to do is
is there a meta position of all of this
crazy paradigm
that we could do without babble and not
in some top-down authoritarian way but
actually sense make
so then we could actually have
sovereignty so we can network ourselves
together and right this shit before it
fucking collapses
yes that's what i'm hearing yeah so the
map to me hold this because i'm i'm
following you completely but i want to
make sure that it's actually being held
more broadly
um and i'm not sure if this metaphor is
going to work but just to kind of do the
two to three just keep moving back and
forth yep
you know if i talk about coherence at
the level of mind i guess mind one and
two there's something that happens there
it seems like an epileptic seizure is a
really nice clean example of what
happens when that coherence breaks down
there's a series of feedback loops the
signaling structures and mechanisms of
an inhibition and excitation that
when the neurocognitive architecture is
coherent it
works right it produces a a set of
emergent properties that are available
in this new space called mind2
that can generate behaviors and
counterfactuals and all that kind of
stuff right
and right now what we're sort of
witnessing in mind three
is the equivalent the moral equivalent
of an epileptic seizure
because we don't yet have the kinds of
significant structures and inhibition
and excitatory feedback loops to
maintain
coherence if we can't attain coherence
then
something locks at that point and we're
doing something new
on that substrate 100 percent can't be
it couldn't
decide better absolutely yeah i think
that lines up
with what what i what i've been trying
to articulate too
or at least the project i'm concerned
with that i've seen it is constantly
in resonance with coca-cola right so
john aren't we trying to distribute deal
logos to bring people together
in interpersonal participatory harmony
right
and then pull the logic so that our
propositional systems align
and then if we can extract a particular
kind of justifiable knowledge
right and then hone in around that to
create some sort of integrated pluralism
that gives people enough
distributed cognition of where they're
going but has enough integration
so that there's a degree of clarity and
coherence and harmony
like that that's the infrastructure to
hold
the emergent system in a way that's at
least puts the constraints on it
that allows it to grow but doesn't
predetermine what you can't predetermine
in this kind of
uh emerging flux i agree with all of
that greg except
i would add to it and i think it goes
with it well
is that deal logos it's not just
argumentation it's drama there's right
so right you have to
all the perspective and participatory
knowing has to be transformed through
some
enacted symbolism right if that's what's
going on in the location
and exactly and that's so consistent why
the hell did i turn this goddamn thing
into a garden
right and a car cartoon my dad said
that's a fucking cartoon you know i was
like
but it's like this art i was i was a
humanistic calling and i was doing all
science like of course i'm a
practitioner as well but i'm trying to
bridge and all of a sudden it's like
the next transformation is gonna have to
have
that synthesis of science and humanities
is going to have to embrace
the entire totality of human experience
we can't have a master in his emissary
uh you know break as we did in the 20th
century we got to bring back
participatory
knowing we got to bring back the entire
thing has got to come around it's
transitioning into communities and and
creating that synthesis and
so is it is it i mean i've got three
things that are sort of coming up
as being the well necessary and i don't
know if they're sufficient
so so one has to do with i guess there's
the two phases of bullshit
one is the interfacing there's the outer
facing so
don't bullshit yourself and don't
bullshit me
um and then and then the third has to do
with this the the grammar
and just be very careful to not um
hmm it's funny if there's a recursion
here and self-referentiality
be very careful to not equivocate
be very careful to achieve
clarity in the communications
methodology yes and be very aware
of when and where i have to speak a
little faster unfortunately because it's
coming too quickly
when a niche for bullshit has opened up
in the ambiguity of the communications
methodology
yes brilliant
and and why that's particularly
dangerous and requires us to be careful
and full of care let's use both senses
of that word
careful and full of care um is
that what we're talking about here is
not as a static grasping of what is but
an aspiration
right to transformation and the problem
with transformation
is it moves you into non-logical
identity it takes you out of script
and i've made this argument before you
can't infer your way through
radical transformation it doesn't work
so
that's why we have narrative narrative
trains us in non-logical identity
right it takes it so you can look at the
picture of yourself as a four-year-old
and go there i am
which is like what right and you just do
it without thinking because narrative
has trained you
a non-logical idea of identity and
symbol trains you in non-logic and you
have to teach kids all of this
and we teach them in dialogue how to do
this we're training them in non-logical
identity because
that is what affords them it opens up
the counter factual space
and makes it transformatively available
to them they can
ident they can go through aspirational
transformation
but the problem is non-logical identity
superficially looks like contradiction
looks like ambiguity looks like
equivocation
it's and so that is particularly right
for bullshit
yeah right there
that's why i'm engaging in for me
this whole project of the year logos and
all of these wonderful conversations
because i think this is about trying to
simultaneously create the new cultural
cognitive grammar
but also afford the transformations
right
a perspective and participatory knowing
that hone my skills and virtues
so i can distinguish and discern between
the bullshit and the the non-logical
identity of transformation
i think it's so good yeah so it's
remember we've used that language i
think i've
i've talked about in terms of like does
it does the thing rotate this where does
it rotate
that way and you talk about in terms of
reciprocal closing and reciprocal
opening
exactly yeah like if you've got your
stack upside down
so that relevance realization is no
longer grounding you to the whole of
reality
you're in deep trouble in exactly this
location
yeah and what i was just doing by the
way is i was just like as much
as possible like seating myself in the
stack being in the right direction
listening to you
and noticing like how the the felt sense
of of relevance realization was like
guiding my and orienting and making you
doing that
spectalization of what was happening so
i was able to orient on exactly the
right thing
and everything was saying yes yes yes
yes yes yes we're definitely
i didn't have to worry about the
propositional stuff hanging together
because i was
safe in the space of the exploration of
the emergent possible
when you actually open things up but if
you're not grounded in your
in your relevance realization um and
particularly if you're topsy-turvy
then opening that thing up is is you
know
well it's going to be a real problem
absolutely man so
and you said jordan you said something
you know super simple but also super
profound that i won't come back to you
bullshit self bullshit other okay so
in the unified theory you have your
private narrator mind three
all right and then you sit on top of
that your mind two experiential self
that then embeds itself in its mind one
okay the mind one into mine too is you
know i use the short end well i'll be
dialogue with john about this called the
attentional filter
okay which basically is shorthand for
all the stuff john's talking about bring
stuff in relevance realization bring it
into perspectival knowing
and you know and we'll be dealing with
that then you have the narrator that's
that's then that narrator is going to
bullshit self okay and i call that the
freudian filter
all right because that self needs to be
like hey i'm a good person
you know and needs to believe that it's
doing the right thing and it's
internalized mom and dad's rules and is
a good thing living it up blah blah blah
and we know cognitive dissonance is all
about that
maintaining a justified state of being
and you can analyze this empirically
it's unbelievably robust
and then there's the private to public
filter you know what i call the rogerian
filter because i'm a clinician it's also
line and bullshit
or what you're trying to do to just
maintain the public image and not
avoid the judgment of other okay so then
you bullshit say oh yeah i love that
sweater or oh god i'm
whatever the book you want right you
know so you love me and i get social
influence
so it is learning that calibration at
the social and personal level
how do you calibrate bullshit self
bullshit other and then we have the
whole analytic problem
and and we we've inherited grammars that
are not fucking up to the task and so
now we get this whole issue of like
well good luck actually trying to make
sense when your forefathers fucking
can't make sense
you know you're not handed the grammar
that's needed in the situation you find
yourself in or at least we have to
rediscover and re-put together uh
philosophically and we
we get that right we get the analytic we
get the social we get the personal
uh and we're at least aware of that and
we come into harmony with that
and the right deal logos fucking
you know it's really cool um i don't
know if you if this is something you do
but if you if you run a simulation
um on every do you guys remove the term
with the ess right the evolutionarily
stable strategy
um that which is not an ess is uh
self-terminating i mean if you run it
out long enough it goes to
evaporates so i just ran a little micro
simulation on that so
i would like to propose that every
single strategy that is not
on the line that you're describing which
is to say every single strategy
that is on the line of self-bullshit
every single strategy that's on the line
of other bullshit
uh is a is self-terminating
this is uh whitehead's claim our one
hope is that evil is ultimately
self-destructive
yeah i i'm going to propose that i can i
can
prove it although i don't know that i
can prove it in propositional language
just yet
right i i think wisely we know that
that's true over time
i will say you know villains you know
you know in their lives
they get away with shit well this is the
problem right we have a
humans have a time horizon you know if
if your civilization
every single civilization collapses but
they all collapse in a thousand years
you've got like you know
15 generations that are like yeah it's
cool what are you talking about and then
those those last few generations are
like confused
what's going on why is why is everything
getting worse i don't get it right and
then and then you have this
horrible crisis and everybody just sort
of loses their minds right
history becomes utterly lost grammar
becomes
you know put into a into a blender and
then you kind of reboot on this new
basis and you start again like oh wait
okay we're cool so
it has to do i think a little bit with
time horizons that are right exactly
it dumps entropic externalities
into the shit of the system and that's
going to back it up eventually
right exactly and that's going to back
it up eventually and so you end up with
there will be a reckoning
um but there are ways to sort of you
might die in advance of that
yeah yeah exactly it's like the inverse
of the guy who plants the tree he's
i was participating big history
conference and it was be a good ancestor
that's what it that's what it that was
the title of it's like yes you know you
want to extend yourself in time you want
to be on the right side of history be a
damn good answer
don't leave your bullshit you know to
your future self don't leave it to
others and don't leave it to your
kids yeah and so here's the other piece
of it i think this other piece is also
super super important
um which is to say that the good news
and it's like the best
possible news is that and also
so we're not saying don't eat cotton
candy eat broccoli
i would say we're not saying defer your
local quality of well-being in exchange
for
people you'll never know that's a that's
a that's a thing but it's not the right
thing
what i'm saying at least and i believe
that we will collectively say is and
also
this particular location this this this
spot in justification space
also happens to be the location that has
the highest possible meaningfulness
of your present being in the world
and so you get the thing that is
actually the thing that is the most
valuable in your life while you are
alive and happen also simultaneously
to be participating in that thing that
is
most enduring well actually can not is
not self-terminating
yeah so when kant kant talks about
well-being essentially he's got a
wonderful summary of it is happiness
with the worthiness to be happy okay so
so when you're bullshitting you're
cutting away at that worthiness
right so it's that dialect it's you know
yes we want happiness
and don't do it don't you know you're
losing it if you're sacrificing it
without integrity
you know if you're bullshitting to get
there it's worthiness to be and it is
that diet that's a dialectic of that
it's in an integrated piece and holding
that
i think that's bringing up haunt and
happiness is a great
segue then for me because
i think this is one of the most
bullshitty words we have in our culture
right now which is
oh god i know that's i usually hate it
but when i stumble across the kantian
edition i was like all right i can now
bring this term back
and the greeks have multiple terms for
it uh as they always do where we have
one
i often feel like we're four year olds
with our clunky terms and the greeks
have these
same thing with love i mean holy shit
love and wisdom we have one word they
have sophia they have
right so anyways
so sort of the modern stuff on or the
the recent
stuff on this seems to be going this way
like i said there's a lot of conceptual
confusion
but there's a parsing that i think is
emerging
and to take happiness and to pull it
apart
from three things that we put together
success
subjective well-being and meaning in
life and they can all and they are not
identical because they can vary
independently from each other
you do need a certain amount of success
in order to have subjective well-being
subjective well-being is a sense of
the autonomy and competence and
connectedness of the self it sort of
solidifies the self
right that that that that that's what
subjective well-being is
and and if you don't if you're in
poverty or if you're oppressed
right if you don't have enough success
in your life then
you don't have good subjective
well-being the thing is though and this
is what the research shows
once you get out of poverty right then
huge changes in wealth and power only
bring small changes in subjective
well-being
so after a certain stage success and
subjective well-being
peel apart from each other well he said
oh then what
is it what ultimately matters is
subjective well-being no
because subjective well-being is not the
same thing as meaning in life
meaning in life is about ultimately
mattering to
an intelligible order that is greater
than yourself
that's why you can right and so that's
why
what goes down when you have a kid
subjective well-being
why do people do it because meaning in
life goes up right
and so what we have to understand is
that
when we're proposing what you're
proposing well i'm proposing to you
jordan that
when we say to people look you know
commit well first of all
mattering to an intelligible order then
greater than you that is actually
meaning in life
and and and joy is not the same thing as
subjective well-being
subjective well-being is is the positive
sense that yourself
has been solidified and strengthened joy
is
the sense of losing yourself in
something beyond yourself
like in awe and wonder and what we have
to unders what we have to
get people to see is but you should and
this is what you know the stuff i'm
doing with the epicureans in the
in that in the morning sanger classes
you have to prioritize these in the
right way
you shouldn't identify them and you have
to prioritize them in the right way
it's like maslow's hierarchy in some
ways you got to get enough success
so that you've got enough subjective
well-being but you know what you
ultimately really want
you ultimately want meaning in life
because those other all those first two
reliably go down with old age and we
many people
think that's why they're terrified of
old age because they can reliably and
accurately predict
success and subjective well-being are
going to go down but you know if you
measure
old people older people they actually
are
much happier than us how can that be
because their meaning in life is going
up tremendously because they have
in general we're talking
probabilistically not individually
they have more wisdom and they have more
sense of mattering to things beyond
themselves
and so we have to pull up happy this
this notion we have of happiness
is one of the most bullshitty things we
have right now and we have to pull them
apart
right we the babble around that the
seventh branch the one with the red
circle on that that's an analysis
of what well-being is uh that's the and
and what john's talking about it's like
how do we non-equivocate on what the
fuck do we mean by well-being
and a lot of what john said is it would
be embedded in that uh analysis but yeah
yeah and make sure that what we seek is
well-being is the argument and then a
rich analysis of what the components of
well-being
are sorry i was
my mind wanted a little bit of an eddy
but i think it might be useful um
so i was thinking about the fact of the
good news and then as we were talking i
was then thinking oh
yeah and there's also bad news so the
good news is that like wow we're really
we've actually got some pretty seriously
high quality stuff like there's actually
um a lot of hard questions
if you're able to not bullshit yourself
not bullshit others and then move
skillfully
through clarity um we can we can make
some good ground
the bad news is it's really really
fucking hard to do brain surgery in the
middle of an
epileptic season it's the
[Laughter]
i've wept a couple of times at night
with that basic realization so i agree
yeah yeah and this is where i
often part company from my religious
friends
okay and and certain of my ideological
friends because i do not believe there's
a t
loss to history
i don't i don't i don't i don't i don't
have that kind of faith
and and um and that's why i'm also very
suspicious of utopian visions etc
so that's where i would say to you
jordan
that yeah doing it while you're having
the epileptic seizure
uh when when when like like myself i'm
just speaking for myself but perhaps
also for you guys
but when you don't believe that there's
any inevitable t
loss um then it's yeah
i think that's why discussion we're all
having about a reinvention of faith
and reason and continuity of contact and
wisdom is so important because
i i guess for me what else is there
what else is there that we can do um i i
agree with you jordan it's a race
and there's i i i i actually think the
probabilities
are against us but i think the moral
argument
is we've got to try our best and even if
we fail maybe we can light enough
candles
so that there'll be enough light for the
next group of people
that's now that's what i i i like teru
and uh albert kim was the play i want to
know how to be a saint without god
uh at least the everyday the common
conception of god
and so for me that's that's how i think
of it it's like
yes it's the probabilities are we're
gonna lose
but the moral argument is well
there's we have to try our best with the
best people that we can and with the
best
skills we have and even if we fail if we
do a good enough job
that maybe we have sufficed enough
satisfies enough
that we've lit enough candles so there's
enough light for the next group of
people
well and i would say i would say the
same thing but from the interior of that
which is um if you're operating in this
way
what you discover is that there is no
other way to operate
so i don't have to imagine a t-list i
don't have to imagine a better future
all i have to do is act in the way that
i know is the right way to act
and i will in fact do there's a perfect
isometry i mean perfect
they are identical they are the same
thing they're just looking at them from
two different perspectives
i agree with that i think that's well
said that and that to me
i mean mclennan in his book on the
wisdom of a patient talks about
you know the three degrees you start
with the epicureans that's like primary
school then you move into the
uh high school that's the stoics and
then you move into university that's the
new playlist but what you just said
about that
that's that's that's a very stoic thing
right
that uh right um and um yeah
so i agree with that we're fucked guys
let's just go get drunk
i mean you know there it is you know
what you were in this trajectory and
yeah i'm scared of shit you know
um but what you said jordan and what you
both said i mean what
you're now all of a sudden when you wake
up in a particular way and you're
aligned in a particular way and it just
unfolds in some ways i mean just because
like the virtue like aristotle talked
about in terms of you cultivate a
particular kind of line of virtue
and the structure essentially starts to
unfold itself
this is sarcasm this is the verb this is
the virtue that we do not have a word
for
because of sun is to have this
this you know this training of your
stalin's landscaping
so that you are you are tempted to
attempt it to the good
what is it i actually yeah i don't know
yeah it's what's it's one of the
cardinal virtues
i should probably know it then it's
usually translated as moderation
but it doesn't affect it or temperance
which doesn't capture it
in fact many people have tried to argue
that maybe the closest thing we now have
in our culture
for soccer isn't it something closer
like mindfulness uh mcgee argues that in
his book
so i don't translate it socrates and
socrates is in contrast in practice
and kravia is you know pratya the
mosquati of the power of the people
and krathya is in is to exert power on
yourself so you
this is when you're restraining yourself
like don't take the cake
don't take the kids right but it's right
but but wait
sophiston is is uh is like is
to to to be just not
is to be naturally tempted to the good
right right this is the difference
between the kantian and
aristotle vision of morality right yes i
mean kant's view
the deontological view is you have to
cultivate the discipline to control
the sin essentially and the strength of
morality is the ability to regulate that
in essence
and the aristotle view is to figure out
a way to train the system so that they
are aligned toward the virtue so that
there isn't they are in harmony
right that's what i mean and and and and
notice the weird
aspirational nature of temptation before
breath is out
when you're tempted to do evil who's
tempting you it's some
aspect of you and right it's
aspirational but it's a
it's an aspiration that reciprocally
narrows but we can train
aspiration that tempts us to reciprocal
opening
that's soft and if we crack the bullshit
equation right to help people understand
why
their animalistic shit starts and then
they can rationalize and then bullshit
and
we can you know the ability to actually
align that thing
with insight um seems that we can do
better
yeah i think what you said a few minutes
ago
really i hadn't put it but putting those
together soccer
and stoicism because i it always
bothered me that the stoics said
that what they wanted to do was and and
nietzsche this pissed me
off that i it was to it was to
you know to flow with nature and i was
like what nietzsche
or eggs but
what you just said jordan right if you
get into a state where we are
sophisticated when we're suffer senate
right we we feel
we feel naturally aligned in ourselves
and then we feel
naturally aspirationally aligned to the
good
and then that's to always flow towards
the good
and i think it just me i just go to oh
that's it
that's what they're talking about that's
what they're trying to put their finger
on and they use
and and people don't get this because
they think of stoicism as this dollar
thing
the word one of the words that's most
frequently used by the stoics to
describe what they're after
and the name brings us out of this book
is joy
stoicism is supposed to result in joy
not
in kratom but socratic joy
yeah it's funny i i feel like i could uh
i could give uh frederick a uh
just a quick twist and he'd be cool
because the you know to me this the
metaphor is actually very simple it's
like um
you just make it practical like
woodworking or
you know his favorite sculpture you know
saffron scent is to have built a
skillfulness of relationship with the
object
to be able to actually flow with its
natural texture you know michelangelo
nails it right and you just say okay
replace the stone with
life with the whole of life and that's
it right you're done
uh it doesn't it's not easy right it's a
skillful relationship it's actually
building wisdom right build applying
wisdom it's building a
and the naturalness like that's the
problem right the problem is an
assumption of a primordialness as
opposed to a skillfulness
that it's it's not the infant's
naturalness in relationship to nature
it's the truly skillful wise person's
naturalness
to have discovered a way of of sort of
co-creating with what nature is giving
you so you're the artist's
uh masterfulness that's it and
and that right i mean joe john i mean we
go back to our 11th promo consciousness
blog in your analysis right of
the perspectival phenomenological uh you
know participatory grip of self and
relationship to the world when
individuals have that's transcendent
experiences right
it is then coming into relation to the
self into the world
and having a more fine groomed flowing
relationship with the stone with life
it's funny that we now enter we now and
go move to the
the sculpting image because now we've
graduated from stoicism to neoplatonism
because that's was platinus's famous
metaphor for his project
of the uh of the of the anarchic ascent
he said you you you're you are basically
a carved block of stone and you need to
kind of you need to carve away
everything until you release the statue
uh within that was his chosen metaphor
uh for describing
this process and he and and so it's
deeply resonant with everything you just
said george
and also what you just said greg about
you know how it
we now are talking about that that
soccerson can come into
a kind of intensification when people
are having these
awakening and transcendent experiences
very much so
all right check this shit out watch this
so greg taking this the systems of
justification
now drop drop in brother greg who's not
present in this call but he's now
present in a big way so i've got my jazz
trumpeter
and my jazz trumpeter is playing but
he's not cool which is to say he's hung
up
he's worried about whether his system of
justification is being taken right
how well am i doing he's worried about
what's happening of course he's getting
his own way
and you can feel it right it feels
crunchy it feels like it's not
there it's not loose it's not cool and
then you got this other guy this other
guy is
cool which is critical right he's on the
one hand he is not attached right so we
can bring in a little bit of the
of the of the eastern flair right he's
he's so
good with what he's doing that he is no
longer trying
at all and the effortlessness is part of
the flood right but it's again
it's not some random jackass who doesn't
know how to play the trumpet
right right that's also not attached
right that's not what we're talking
about
we're talking about somebody for whom
the skillfulness of flowing allows him
to actually get out of his own way
and let the thing do the thing it's
supposed to do without the least bit of
concern for his interior or the other
folks which is way of producing
beautiful music
and then of course at every once in a
while he'll stop he'll kind of look
around and he's like everybody's like
whoa dude that was awesome it's like
all right i don't know what just
happened but i'm going to keep working
on that vibe because that's where it's
at
exactly so and and essentially then the
mind three
that self-conscious mind three is sort
of checking out and you're just in a
perspectival participatory groove
at an inner subjective inter usually an
impulsive intersubjective way
but i think something else just came out
of that right
it sounded to me jordan i think that
you're talking about now that there's
there's there's two existential modes
within the justification framework
there's an encratia mode which is the
one that we have taken as being
paradigmatic
but there's also socratic yep mode of
justification yeah yeah no it's
not we're trying to seek that right yeah
if we open up and we find that and y'all
light and the shine light
through and there's a pathway
yeah and the cool thing is you can
actually you know when they're when
you're there like there's a way of
actually being there and feeling there
like you know some basketball players
will talk about notion of like when
they're in the zone
yeah they can be aware of being in the
zone they
yeah you gotta be real careful yeah you
gotta be
too real careful that energy and all of
a sudden you're jacking stuff out right
you just basically want that observer
function that narrative all right i'm
just well this guy's fucking on fire
yeah exactly you're just like checking
out going wow i'm
watching this thing but that imagine
that now being truly in the collective
right
oh my god distributed right and can you
imagine the transformation between the
chaos the epileptic chaos and the
collective insanity of psychosis that we
were seeing versus the
yeah yeah i can i can't imagine
well fingers crossed right it's it's
interesting how it circles back in a way
because i mean in one sense we're
talking upwards about sort of the logos
and distributed cognition
but when we get when you get that when
you get collective flow
right you also get an altered state of
consciousness and
right and so it also that's what i meant
about it reverberates back
into right and many people go i didn't
know
and they have this weird anamnesis
experience
this you know i've never been here they
say this paradoxical thing i've never
been here before
but this is truly who i am which is like
what
right but that to me that's the hallmark
of somebody trying to
articulate that they've just
aspirational burst
right in some huge way right they felt
the alignment
and then of course the crucial thing is
to say yes
don't throw words at it man right but
don't do that
that's that's just going to make a mess
of things like let's just let it be
all right
well gentlemen i think this is where we
should let it be this is a perfect let
it be
that was great jazzing i really enjoyed
it um
so um if you guys want this for
your channel or whatever let me know i'm
going to upload it at some point
um on voices with verveiki because i
think this was a gem we just covered so
much and it just took off in
so many ways yeah dude actually send me
the raw link i will actually upload it
as its own object on my channel because
i'm interested in seeing i think that
actually creates a different
yeah it does yeah we the one i just did
the one i just did with um
with paul and jonathan we've released it
on all three channels
and and yeah you get a deal logo so you
get a metadata logos thing happening
it's really cool
i'm setting up my channel so i'll be
adding it whenever so
yeah okay well when when you know so
yeah i'll i'll
i'll i'll send you the file jordan yeah
sounds good
i really enjoyed it guys a lot of fun
take care guys